Finding Aid for Affirmations Lesbian/Gay Community Center Records, 1989-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Affirmations Lesbian/Gay Community Center Records 1989-2004
Affirmations Lesbian/Gay Community Center.
0544 Bj 2 Bj Outsize
Affirmations Lesbian/Gay Community Center was established in 1989 to serve as a resource to lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender individuals in the greater Detroit area. The records consist of meeting minutes, correspondence, and written records pertaining to Affirmations’ fundraising, programming, membership and advocacy activities. Select events are also documented by photographs.
5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were donated by Affirmations Lesbian/Gay Community Center (donor no. 9534 ) in November 2004.
The record group is open. However, access to the records requires the researcher to sign an access agreement preserving confidentiality of names recorded in the files.
Affirmations Lesbian/Gay Community Center was founded in 1989 based on the philosophy that "gay is good, you are not alone." Originally established as offshoot of the Michigan Organization for Human Rights (MOHR), Affirmations provided the greater Detroit area with Switchboard (renamed Helpline in October 1994), a volunteer-staffed telephone support line that has continued as one of the organization's hallmark programs. Since its inception, the non-profit has established community groups; open discussion groups; recreation and social activities; seminars, workshops and training programs; and a significant youth services program.
Jan Stevenson, the first President of the Board of Directors, steered Affirmations in its early stages before assuming the role of Executive Director in 1991. During her tenure, the organization flourished and expanded to approximately 1,700 members at its peak in 1995. Julie Enszer, formerly the Program Director, succeeded Stevenson as Executive Director in late 1995.
Between 1995 and 1997, the youth services program grew to approximately half of the organization's work. In the process, Affirmations developed from its initial role as a support-group to that of a community-builder. To reflect this shift, the organization adopted a new mission statement in 1997: "Affirmations Lesbian/Gay Community Center works to achieve respect and equality for gay, lesbian, bisexual and transgender people through social service programs, advocacy, and education. Affirmations provides services to empower individuals and families, to build a cohesive community and to fulfil our responsibilities in society."
The late-1990s ushered in an era of financial difficulty as Affirmations operated at a loss from 1997 to 1999. This instability was worsened by high staff turnover, including the resignation of the entire staff by September 1999. With the departure of Executive Director Cindy Woodbury, the operation of Affirmations was left to the Board and volunteers until Leslie Ann Thompson assumed the role in October 1999.
Despite the turmoil of 1999, 2000 proved to be the organization's strongest year since 1995. Affirmations continued to develop new programs to service the community, and it responded to changing social attitudes toward the gay community by placing greater emphasis on its youth services and diversity programs.
This collection reflects the operational and planning activities for Affirmations Lesbian/Gay Community Center. It is divided into nine series: Background, Governance, Administration, Grants and Fundraising, Programming, Membership and Volunteers, Advocacy, Publicity, and Photographs. The majority of the collection has been arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically within files.
Subjects:
Affirmations Lesbian/Gay Community Center.; Gay men--Michigan.; Lesbians--Michigan.; Gays--Michigan.; Gay rights--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Background
  The Background series (0.1 linear feet, 1989-2004) contains two folders that provide an overview of Affirmations. The first file, General Overview, features select documents that reflect the organization's overall philosophy and activities. The second file is of special note in that it contains the booklet entitled "The First Fifteen Years: An Anniversary Book" that chronicles the history and lifespan of Affirmations from 1989 to 2004. Additional information about the organization in general can also be found in the beginning of the Membership and Volunteers series.
  - General Overview 1989-2002 (Box 1)
  - "The First Fifteen Years: An Anniversary Book," 1989-2004 (Box 1)
- Governance
  The Governance series (1.0 linear feet, 1989-2002) encompasses the policies, regulations, and Board activities that guide the operation of Affirmations. The bulk of this series, the Meeting Records files, provides detailed minutes of the Board of Directors and committee meetings, including updates on financial, programmatic and planning processes. Note that, in addition to files for individual committees (Building, Fundraising, Membership, Policy, Program, Public Relations, Switchboard and Youth Services), select information might also be found within committee reports to the Board of Directors as a whole. Researchers may wish to use these meeting records to supplement more specific investigation of other series. All Meeting Records are organized chronologically.
  - Articles of Incorporation 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Bylaws 1989-1995 (Box 1)
  - Policies
    - General programs and procedures 1989-2003 (Box 1)
    - Research 1994 (Box 1)
  - Planning 1992-2005 (Box 1)
  - Meeting Records
    - 1989
      - Board of Directors (Box 1)
    - 1990
      - Board of Directors (Box 1)
    - 1991
      - Board of Directors (Box 1)
      - Program Committee (Box 1)
      - Switchboard Committee (Box 1)
    - 1992
      - Board of Directors January-June 1992 (Box 1)
      - Board of Directors July-December 1992 (Box 1)
      - Policy Committee (Box 1)
      - Program Committee (Box 1)
      - Switchboard Committee (Box 1)
    - 1993
      - Board of Directors January-June 1993 (Box 1)
      - Board of Directors July-December 1993 (Box 1)
      - Building Committee (Box 1)
      - Membership/Fundraising Committees (Box 1)
      - Switchboard Committee (Box 1)
      - Youth Services Committee (Box 1)
    - 1994
      - Board of Directors January-June 1994 (Box 1)
      - Board of Directors July-December 1994 (Box 1)
      - Fundraising Committee (Box 1)
      - Membership Committee (Box 1)
      - Program Committee (Box 1)
      - Public Relations Committee (Box 1)
      - Switchboard Committee (Box 1)
      - Youth Services Committee (Box 1)
    - 1995
      - Board of Directors January-June 1995 (Box 1)
      - Board of Directors July-December 1995 (Box 1)
      - Fundraising/Development Committee (Box 2)
    - 1996
      - Board of Directors January-June 1996 (Box 2)
      - Board of Directors July-December 1996 (Box 2)
- Administration
  The daily activities and management of Affirmations can be found in the Administration series (0.75 linear feet, 1990-2002). This includes several large Correspondence files whose content ranges from thank you notes sent by members to letters pertaining to the programs and activities of the organization. Researchers can gain a less formal view on Affirmations through these letters, which often provide a personal perspective on the circumstances surrounding the organization and its issues. Program and general planning, success metrics and staff notes can be found in the Reporting files.
  - Annual Reports 1990-1993 (Box 2)
  - Financials
    - 1994 (Box 2)
    - 1995 (Box 2)
  - Human Resources 1991-1998 (Box 2)
  - Community Center Survey 1998 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - 1990 (Box 2)
    - January-June 1991 (Box 2)
    - July-December 1991 (Box 2)
    - 1992 (Box 2)
    - 1993 (Box 2)
    - 1994 (Box 2)
    - 1995 (Box 2)
    - 1996-2001 (Box 2)
  - Reporting
    - Year-end group reports 1993-1998 (Box 2)
    - Volunteer activity reports 1993 (Box 2)
    - Staff/program reports
      - 1996 (Box 2)
      - 1997 (Box 2)
      - 1998 (Box 2)
      - 1999 (Box 2)
    - Staff meetings
      - 2001 (Box 2)
      - 2002 (Box 2)
- Grants and Fundraising
  The Grants section of the Grants and Fundraising series (0.75 linear feet, 1989-2001) is organized alphabetically by sponsor organization and includes submitted proposals and tracking for programs approved for funding. Many of these programs represent partnerships with other organizations to complement and supplement the groups and activities hosted solely by Affirmations. The Fundraising section of the Grants and Fundraising series represents select events designed to raise money for the organization. An additional revenue stream can be found in the Membership series through member dues and pledges. Administrative records of monetary planning can be found in the meeting records for the Board of Directors and/or the Fundraising Committee records.
  - Grants
    - General tracking 1998-2001 (Box 2)
    - Applications 1990-1993 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous applications 1990-1994 (Box 2)
    - Alternatives for Girls (AFG) 1998 (Box 2)
    - ASTRAEA 1994 (Box 2)
    - Chicago Resource Center (CRC)
      - 1989 (Box 3)
      - 1990 (Box 3)
      - 1991 (Box 3)
      - 1992 (Box 3)
      - 1994 (Box 3)
    - Colin Higgins Foundation, Camp 1997 (Box 3)
    - Daimler Chrysler Corporation Fund 2000 (Box 3)
    - Family Independence Agency (FIA)
      - 1994-1995 (Box 3)
      - 1996 (Box 3)
      - 1998 (Box 3)
    - Hope Fund 1995-1996 (Box 3)
    - INSURE AIDS Grants 1992-1994 (Box 3)
    - Michigan AIDS Foundation (MAF)
      - 1996-1997 (Box 3)
      - 1997-1998 (Box 3)
      - 1998-1999 (Box 3)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 3)
    - Midwest AIDS Prevention Project (MAPP) 1996-1997 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Women's Foundation (MWF)
      - 1999-2000 (Box 3)
      - 2001 (Box 3)
    - Oakland County Health Division/Office of Substance Abuse (Building Bridges)
      - 1991 (Box 3)
      - 1994-1995 (Box 3)
      - 1996-1997 (Box 3)
      - 1997-1998 (Box 3)
      - 1998-1999 (Box 3)
    - Points of Light Foundation 1992 (Box 3)
    - Victims of Crime Act (VOCA) 1993 (Box 3)
  - Fundraising
    - Donations and contributions 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - April in Gay Paris 1996 (Box 3)
    - Human Rights Campaign Fund Dinner 1990 (Box 3)
    - Silent Auction
      - 1991 (Box 3)
      - 1993 (Box 3)
      - 1994 (Box 3)
      - 1996 (Box 3)
- Programming
  The core functions of Affirmations can be found in the Programming series (1.0 linear feet, 1990-2002). The Events files present flyers publicizing the activities and events sponsored by Affirmations. This is followed by more extensive sections chronicling the planning, development and evaluation of specific events and activities. Programs have been categorized according to the nature of their function, as Recreation and Social Activities or as Community and Open Discussion Groups. Two additional areas of programming, the flagship Switchboard/Helpline and the increasingly important Youth Services, have been individually featured to include all procedural developments pertaining to these areas, from training to tracking to publicity. Further information about Youth Services might also be found in the Facilitators section of the Membership and Volunteers series. Researchers may also wish to consult the meeting records for the Board of Directors, Program Committee, Switchboard Committee and/or the Youth Services Committee for more administrative information.
  - Events
    - Flyers 1990-1994 (Box 3)
    - Flyers 1995 (Box 3)
    - Flyers 1996 (Box 3)
    - Flyers 1997 (Box 3)
    - Flyers 1998-1999 (Box 3)
    - Flyers 2000-2001 (Box 3)
    - Flyers, Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Pride Banquet
    - 1991 (Box 3)
    - 1992 (Box 3)
    - 1993 (Box 3)
    - 1994 (Box 3)
    - 1995 (Box 3)
    - 1996 (Box 3)
    - 1997 (Box 3)
    - 1998 (Box 3)
    - 1999 (Box 3)
  - Recreation and Social Activities
    - Art Gallery 2000 (Box 3)
    - Children Of Lesbians And Gays Everywhere (COLAGE) 2001 (Box 3)
    - Lesbian/Bisexual Women's Leadership Project 1995 (Box 3)
    - Michigan/Ohio Summit 1994 (Box 3)
    - Palmer Fund 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - Softball, swim teams 1990, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Team Great Lakes 1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - Community and Open Discussion Groups
    - Services, General 1990-2001 (Box 4)
    - Forms (Box 4)
    - Informational packet: lesbians of color (Box 4)
    - Coming Out group 1990-1996 (Box 4)
    - Creating Change 1995 (Box 4)
    - Faith in Action 1994-1996 (Box 4)
    - GALAXIE 1997-1998 (Box 4)
    - In-Touch groups 1990-2002 (Box 4)
    - Workshops: Breaking up/Flirting & Dating 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - Switchboard/Helpline
    - Policy and Procedure Manual 1990-1993 (Box 4)
    - Community Referral and Information Services (CRIS) sub-committee 1993-1994 (Box 4)
    - Forms (Box 4)
    - Training
      - 1992 (Box 4)
      - 1993-1994 (Box 4)
      - 1996 (Box 4)
      - 1997 (Box 4)
      - 1998 (Box 4)
      - 2001 (Box 4)
      - 2002 (Box 4)
    - Advertising/Publicity 1994 (Box 4)
    - Switchboard Communicator newsletter 1991-1995 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence with volunteers 1992-1999 (Box 4)
    - Shift Leaders 1993-1996 (Box 4)
    - Statistics 1991-1995 (Box 4)
  - Youth Services
    - General information 1992-1996 (Box 4)
    - Volunteer job descriptions (Box 4)
    - Reference binder: youth services 1997-1998 (Box 4)
    - Informational packet: youth volunteers (Box 4)
    - Informational packet: youth lesbians (Box 4)
    - Informational packet: mentor program (Box 4)
    - Informational packet: mentor training (Box 4)
    - Mentorship Project 1995-1999 (Box 4)
    - Peer Educators conference 1998-1999 (Box 4)
    - Street Outreach/youth volunteers 1997 (Box 4)
    - Transitions 1994-1995 (Box 4)
    - Youth in Transition 1994-1997 (Box 4)
- Membership and Volunteers
  The recruitment, training and general information for members can be found in the Membership and Volunteers series (0.75 linear feet, 1990-2000). The information and recruitment files are especially useful for general overviews of Affirmations, its philosophy, programs and overall presentation to the public. Several programs requiring trained volunteers have been isolated, most notably the Facilitators, who made the groups and other signature programs possible. Appreciation events, such as retreats and awards banquets, have also been included in this series.
  - Membership
    - Information and recruitment 1990-1995 (Box 4)
  - Volunteers
    - Volunteer information and recruitment 1993-2000 (Box 4)
    - Volunteer job descriptions (Box 4)
    - General volunteer training 1993-1996 (Box 4)
    - Greeters 1993-2000 (Box 4)
    - Peer Counseling
      - Brochures and publicity (Box 4)
      - Development 1999 (Box 4)
    - Training: Peer Educators 1994 (Box 4)
    - Training: Speaker's Bureau 1992 (Box 5)
    - Speaker's Bureau in-service 1995 (Box 5)
  - Facilitators
    - Brochures and recruitment (Box 5)
    - Policy and Procedure manual 1992 (Box 5)
    - Administration and evaluation 1992-1999 (Box 5)
    - Youth facilitator meeting minutes 1994-2000 (Box 5)
    - Training
      - Training manual (Box 5)
      - Development manuals, to 1994 (Box 5)
      - Development manuals 1996 (Box 5)
      - Development manuals 1997 (Box 5)
      - Development manual 1999 (Box 5)
    - Retreats
      - 1993 (Box 5)
      - 1994 (Box 5)
      - 1997 (Box 5)
  - Volunteer Awards Banquet
    - 1992 (Box 5)
    - 1993 (Box 5)
    - 1994 (Box 5)
    - 1995 (Box 5)
    - 1996 (Box 5)
    - 1997 (Box 5)
    - 1998 (Box 5)
    - 1999 (Box 5)
  - Service Awards 1998 (Box 5)
- Advocacy
  The external face of Affirmations can be found in part in the Advocacy (0.25 linear feet, 1990-2001) series. This focuses on specific events or issues campaigned for or supported by Affirmations and is arranged alphabetically by the name of the event or cause.
  - Outreach/Education 1992-1995 (Box 5)
  - A Day of Remembrance 2001 (Box 5)
  - Allen Park 1996 (Box 5)
  - Amendment 2 (Colorado) 1990 (Box 5)
  - Amedure murder 1995 (Box 5)
  - Community Advocate Training Program (CATP) 1995 (Box 5)
  - Domestic partnerships 1995 (Box 5)
  - Election 1996 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Bias Crime Task Force 1994-1995 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Campaign for Human Dignity 1993-1994 (Box 5)
  - National Coming Out Day 1992-1996 (Box 5)
- Publicity
  The external face of Affirmations can also be found in the Publicity (0.2 linear feet, 1989-2003) series. This is organized chronologically and includes newspaper clippings and other stories about or pertaining to the organization. Also included are letters to editors and journalists in which Affirmations commends or condemns their coverage of gay and lesbian issues.
  - To 1990 (Box 5)
  - 1991 (Box 5)
  - 1992 (Box 5)
  - 1993-1996 (Box 5)
  - 1999-2002 (Box 5)
  - Detroit Free Press, 1990-2003 (Box 5)
- Photographs
  The final series, Photographs (0.2 linear feet, estimated 1997-2000), contains a selection of images depicting select events and activities. The year and date for some events have been provided, but the timeframe for many is unknown. They are projected to have occurred between 1997 and 2000.
  - Big Bash 2000 (Box 5)
  - Big Bash/Silent Auction (Box 5)
  - Fundraisers (Box 5)
  - Outdoor fundraisers (Box 5)
  - Tour de France (Box 5)
  - Pride Banquet (Box 5)
  - Pride events (Box 5)
  - Pridefest 2002 (Box 5)
  - Come Out and Laugh 2000 (Box 5)
  - A Day of Remembrance 2002 (Box 5)
  - Domestic Partnership registry 2003 (Box 5)
  - Health Fair 2003 (Box 5)
  - Affirmations/Backstreet Prom 1997-1998 (Box 5)
  - Prom 1999 (Box 5)
  - Social Activities (Box 5)
  - Volunteer Retreat 1997 (Box 5)
  - A Night in Hollywood 2000 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
Related Material
Additional information about Affirmations can be found in a collection of newsletters produced by the organization and sent to Affirmations members and the general community. These have been catalogued in two record groups: Affirmations Lesbian/Gay Community Center 1989-1999 and Centerlines 1999-2004.
Other related record groups are separately cataloged and available through MIRLYN. Collections of potential interest are:
Between the Lines (1993-2003)
Affirmations Web Archives (2010-2013) http://webarchives.cdlib.org/site/sw1668957d
Craig Covey Papers (1987-2001)
Michigan Campaign for Human Dignity (1992-1994)
Michigan Organization for Human Rights (MOHR) Records (1973-1994)
Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays, Ann Arbor Chapter (1984-1996)
Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays, Detroit Chapter (1986-1996)
Parents, Families and Friends of Lesbians and Gays, Lansing Chapter (1972-1999)
James W. Toy Papers (1963-1995)
Triangle Foundation Records (1987-1999, bulk 1990-1994)
Washtenaw Rainbow Action Project (1993-2000)